Schwimmer-Lloyd Collection, 1912-1950
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
Schwimmer-Lloyd collection
1912-1950
Schwimmer, Rosika, 1877-1948
MS 141
4 boxes, 1 poster (1.25 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
Suffragist; feminist; pacifist; organizer, Ford Peace Expedition; and diplomat. The collection documents primarily the peace activism of Rosika Schwimmer, but also include some material on co-activist and friend, Lola Maverick Lloyd. Biographical materials are included for a number of friends and associates including Lola Maverick Lloyd, Jane Addams, Carrie Chapman Catt, Henry Ford, Charlotte Perkins Gilman, Harvey O'Connor, Eleanor Roosevelt, and Franciska Schwimmer. Other materials include clippings, correspondence, writings, personal memorabilia, subject files, and photographs.
Rosika Schwimmer (1877-1948) was born in Budapest, Hungary, the oldest child of Max B. Schwimmer, a grocer and horse dealer, and Bertha Katscher Schwimmer, member of a distinguished Jewish literary family. She married in 1911 but divorced two years later. An accomplished linguist, fluent in more than half a dozen languages, Schwimmer initially devoted herself to the cause of woman suffrage. She attended the 1904 Berlin meeting of the International Council of Women at which the International Women's Suffrage Alliance was founded. She settled in London in 1911 as press secretary of the Alliance. With the outbreak of World War I, Schwimmer focused her efforts on peace. In 1914 she traveled to the U.S. to speak with President Wilson and Secretary of State William Jennings Bryan on behalf of the Alliance's endorsement of neutral mediation of the war. Her flamboyant personality and ardent peace advocacy provided the spark that kindled sentiment for the Woman's Peace Party. She was also influential in organizing the 1915 Congress of Women at The Hague and establishing the International Committee of Women for Permanent Peace (later Women's International League for Peace and Freedom (WILPF)). The Ford Peace Ship, the ocean liner sponsored by Henry Ford that sailed to Europe in 1915-16 carrying an unofficial mediation commission, brought its passengers, including Schwimmer, a notoriety that led to her resignation from WILPF in 1918. Upon her return to Hungary, Schwimmer was appointed ambassador to Switzerland. In 1921 she returned to the U.S. where her attempts to resume her career and gain citizenship were thwarted by accusations that she was a spy. Her final citizenship application was denied in 1924 when she refused to affirm her willingness to bear arms in defense of the United States. She remained in the U.S. as an alien for the rest of her life, supported by her old friend and co-worker for peace, Lola Maverick Lloyd.
Lola Maverick Lloyd (1875-1944) graduated from Smith College in 1897. A pioneer suffragist and pacifist, in 1915 she co-founded with Jane Addams the Women's Peace Party, and later the Women's International League for Peace and Freedom. She was also a delegate to the Congress of Women at the Hague in 1915 and sailed on Henry Ford's Peace Ship. Lloyd and Schwimmer co-chaired the Campaign for World Government.
This collection consists of duplicates from the Schwimmer-Lloyd Collection at the New York Public Library. The material contained here documents primarily the peace activism of Rosika Schwimmer. It includes biographical articles, clippings, correspondence, writings, personal memorabilia, subject files, and photographs. It also includes biographical materials on numerous friends and associates including Lola Maverick Lloyd, Jane Addams, Carrie Chapman Catt, Henry Ford, Charlotte Perkins Gilman, Harvey O'Connor, Eleanor Roosevelt, and Franciska Schwimmer.
This collection is organized into five series:
I. Biographical Materials (Rosika Schwimmer)
II. Friends and Associates
III. Subject Files
IV. Peace
V. Oversize Materials
Books on Shelf
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
The collection is open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection.
History of the Collection
The collection was donated to the Sophia Smith Collection by Rosika Schwimmer. These are duplicates from the Schwimmer-Lloyd Collection, an archive on women's rights, suffrage, peace movements, and world government at the New York Public Library in New York City.
Search Terms
Lloyd, Lola Maverick, 1875-1944; Schwimmer, Rosika, 1877-1948; Campaign for World Government; Henry Ford Peace Expedition (1915-1916); Feminists--History--Sources; International cooperation--History--Sources; International cooperation--History--Sources; Pacifists--United States--History--Sources; Peace movements--History--20th century--Sources; Women--International cooperation--History--Sources; World War, 1914-1918--Protest movements--Sources; Women and peace--History--20th century--Sources
Additional Information
Related Material
Related material can be found in the Jessie Lloyd O'Connor Papers in the Sophia Smith Collection; and a small collection of Lola M. Lloyd Papers in the Smith College Archives.
Additional papers of Rosika Schwimmer and Lola Maverick Lloyd are at the Hoover Institution; Swarthmore College Peace Collection; the Library of Congress; and the Ford Archives in Dearborn, Michigan.
- Contents: finding aid (Box 1, Folder 1)
- SERIES I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIALS (Rosika Schwimmer)
  - Correspondence
    - About Schwimmer-Lloyd Collection at the New York Public Library Annex, 1974-79, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Rosika Schwimmer, 1934-38 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Biographical articles, 1915-59 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Writings, 1938-48 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1912-48 (Box 1, Folder 6-9)
  - Articles by F. Marvin, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Book reviews, 1928-29 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Memorabilia, 1914-39 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Obituaries, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Mission carrying Wilson's message to Hungary (A Year as a Government Agent, by Vira B. Whitehouse), 1920 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Nobel Peace Prize candidate,1948 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Photographs of Rosika Schwimmer at home, 1946, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
- SERIES II. FRIENDS AND ASSOCIATES
  - Addams, Jane, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Anthony, Susan B. (II), 1936 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Balch, Emily Greene, 1915 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Bayen, Malaku Emmanuel, 1937 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Beard, Mary, 1936 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Blake, Katherine, 1938 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Bullitt, William, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Catt, Carrie Chapman, 1939-47 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Caesar, Irving, 1939, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Davis, Elmer, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Detzer, Dorothy, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Einstein, Albert, 1933 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Ford, Henry, 1937-42 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Gilman, Charlotte Perkins, 1935-36 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Holmes, Oliver Wendell, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Holtby, Winifred, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Lloyd, Lola Maverick, 1931-41 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Lloyd, William B., Jr., 1940 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Maverick, Maury (cousin of Lola Maverick Lloyd), 1935-39 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - O'Connor, Harvey, 1931-53 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Paul, Alice, 1936 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Roosevelt, Eleanor R., 1940-46 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Schwimmer, Franciska, 1944, undated (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Streit, Clarence K., 1939-41 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Villard, Oswald Garrison, undated (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Wynner, Edith, 1945-50 (Box 2, Folder 26)
- SERIES III. SUBJECT FILES
  - Atomic energy, 1945 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Griffin Bill, 1932 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Marvin, Fred: court case, 1928 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - The Magnificent Yankee (play about Rosika Schwimmer), inscribed by F. Schwimmer to the Smith College Library, 1946 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - D.A.R. blacklist, 1928 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Miscellaneous, 1935-42 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Citizenship case, 1927-32, undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Lusitania sinking, 1935 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Miscellaneous foreign publications, 1915-42 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - World Center for Women's Archives, 1935 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Race problems, 1937-46 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Rosika Schwimmer's libel case vs. Fred R. Marvin and Commercial Publishing Company: transcripts, 1924-28 (Box 3)
- SERIES IV. PEACE
  [See also OVERSIZE MATERIALS]
  - Miscellaneous domestic articles, 1924-41 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous foreign articles, 1916-42 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Nazism, 1936-41 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - League of Nations, 1938-39 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Pacifism, 1916-45, undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Einstein (on peace), 1935 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Miscellaneous peace publications, 1915-44 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Cartoons, 1941 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Peace Ship, 1915 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Women's International League for Peace and Freedom
    - Correspondence, 1935-56 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1919-31 (Box 4, Folder 10a)
  - Church and youth groups on peace, 1928-44 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Communism, 1942, undated (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - United Nations, 1944-46 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Peace award, 1937 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - World government, 1924-44 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - War Resister's League, 1940-48 (Box 4, Folder 16)
- SERIES V. OVERSIZE MATERIALS
  - World War I anti-war poster, circa 1914 (Map-case Flat File)
- BOOKS ON SHELF
  - Tisza Tales by Rosika Schwimmer (Garden City, NY: Doubleday, 1928)